NYSUT Oral History Interviews 6174 OH
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Oral History Interviews
1976-2009
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174 OH
11.94 cubic feet
11.4 linear ft.
Oral histories.
Includes audio tapes, VHS video cassettes, computer discs and transcripts
7164215
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, March 16, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 24, 2016
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/017 MB: NYSUT General Officers Memorabilia 6174: NYSUT Records 6174 AV: NYSUT Audio-Visual Materials 6174 MB: NYSUT Memorabilia 6174 P: NYSUT Photographs 6174 PUBS: NYSUT Publications 6174/001: NYSUT President's Office Files 6174/001 P: NYSUT President's Office Photographs 6174/002: NYSUT Vice President's Office files 6174/003: NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services. Files 6174/004: NYSUT Field Services Department Files 6174/004 AV: NYSUT Field Services Department Audio-Visual Material 6174/005: NYSUT Legislative Department Files 6174/006: NYSUT Public Relations Department Files 6174/007: NYSUT New York Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education Files 6174/008: NYSUT Federation of Nurses and Health Professionals Files 6174/009: NYSUT Teacher Education Conference Board Files 6174/010: NYSUT Convention files 6174/011: NYSUT Mid-Hudson Regional Office Files 6174/012: NYSUT "Teachers United: The Rise of NYSUT" Research Notes 6174/013 AV: NYSUT Representative Assembly (RA) Audio-Visual materials 6174/014: NYSUT Alan Lubin Files 6174/015: NYSUT Boards of Directors Meetings 6174/016: NYSUT Vice-President's Office Maria Neira. Files 6174/017: NYSUT General Officers Records 6174/017 AV: NYSUT General Officers Audio-Visual Materials 6174/017 P: NYSUT General Officers Photographs 6174/018: NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services, Maria Neira Files 6174/019: NYSUT Biography File
Teachers' union--New York (State); Fennell, Dorothy; Gaffney, Dennis, 1959-; New York State United Teachers
7164215
- NYSUT Oral History Project - Dorothy Fennell, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Draft as of Oct. 2002. Transcript of interviews by Dorothy Fennel, director, Special Projects for Unions, Cornell University ILR Extension; draft outline for table of contents; introduction describing tension between NEA and AFT; chapters 1-10, containing brief biographies and interviews with Leon Lieberman, Manny Kafka, Tom Hobart, Paul Cole, Bob Allen, Sandy Feldman, Toni Cortese, Don Benker, Jeannette DiLorenzo, Fred Nauman, Gloria Weinman, Sylvia Matousek, Ely Kaplan, Dick Herrmann, Mike Corn, Bill Cea, Bernard Ashe, Al Shanker, Vito DeLeonardis, Walter Tice, Esther Aswad, Doug Matousek, Tony McCann, Herb Magidson, James Wood, Matthew Doherty
- NYSUT Oral History Project Manuscript - D. Fennell, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Oct. 2002. As above.
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 1: A (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Interviews with Robert Allen, 2/1/92, 6/15/00; Bernard Ashe, 6/15/00, 7/6/00; Esther Asward, 4/27/92
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 1: B (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Interviews with Don Benker, 4/6/00; Tony Bifaro, 1/4/02
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 1: Cea-Cole (1999-2002) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Interviews with Bill Cea, 4/7/00; Paul Cole, 9/10/91, 6/15/00
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 1: Corn-Cortese (1999-2002) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Interviews with Mike Corn, 4/6/00; Antonia Cortese, 2/1/92, 6/15/00
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 2: D-O (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Interviews with Vito DeLeonardis, 6/22/00; Jeanette DiLorenzo, 4/27/92; Matthew Doherty, 2/1/92; Sandra Feldman, 4/1/92
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 2: H (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Interviews with Dick Herrmann, 4/7/00; Tom Hobart, 12/10/90, 3/24/92, 1/4/02
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 2: K (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Interviews with Emanuel Kafka, 2/1/92; Ely Kaplan, 4/8/00
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 2: L-M (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Interviews with Leon Lieberman, 2/12/92; Herb Magidson, 2/12/92; Sylvia Matousek, 4/8/00; Fred Nauman, 4/1/00 (no material)
- NYSUT Oral History Vol. 3: P-Z (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Interviews with Robert Padiwodzinski, 7/22/01; Tom Pisa, 1/3/02; Irwin Polishook, 1/17/02
- NYSUT Oral History - Vol.3: R (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Interviews with Hobie Rhinehart, 4/6/00; Ed Robisch, 1/5/02
- NYSUT Oral History Vol.3: S, T, W (1990-2002) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Interviews with Lucille Swain, 4/1/92; Walter Tice, 4/1/92; Gloria Weinman, 4/1/92, 4/6/00; James Wood, 2/1/92
- Index (Box 1, Folder 14)
- NYSUT Oral History Project Interviews --- D. Fennell 1990-2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Box with 11 floppy disks of interviews; index of interviews on audio cassete tapes
- NYSUT Oral History Project - Dennis Gaffney - Index (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Index of audio tapes collected and recorded by Dennis Gaffney, author of Teachers United
- NYSUT Oral History Project - Dennis Gaffney - Notes (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Handwritten notes; letter from Gaffney to NYSUT special projects coordinator, offering to chronicle the history of NYSUT
- NYSUT Oral History - Unionism and Democracy Notebook (Box 3, Folder 3)
  AFT 2004 Constitution and Bylaws
- NYSUT Oral History Unionism and Democracy Notebook (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Conference agenda sponsored by Albert Shanker Institute, introduction, related materials
- NYSUT Oral History Unionism and Democracy Notebook (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Conference materials
- NYSUT Oral History Unionism and Democracy Notebook (Box 3, Folder 6)
- NYSUT -- All In Favor (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Fred Nauman Interview (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Robert Allen. Doc (Box 3, Folder 9)
- NYSUT History -- Dan Sanders, Ray Skuse (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Window Dub; Tape #1, #2, #3 -- 99-82 (1985); Master Edit, Dan Sander's Retirement - #716-81 (1987); Cutaways Comm. 100-1985 - Sandy Feldman
- NYSUT History Interviews - P. Cole; G. Duesberg; W. Dunn (Box 3, Folder 11)
  #0207-20, #0207-19 & #0207-04
- NYSUT History Interviews #2 -- Matt Doherty, Manny Kafka, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Window Dub -- 2/1/1992
- NYSUT History Interviews -- Leon Lieberman, H. Magidson, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  Window Dub -- 2/12/1992 -- #0207-02
- NYSUT History Interviews #1 -- Bob Allen, Antonia Cortese and James Wood, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- NYSUT History Interviews #3 -- Judi Laurence, Tony McCann and Doug Matousek, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Window Dub -- 2/18/1992
- NYSUT History Interview -- Tom Hobart, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Part 1 and 2 -- 12/10/1990 --- #050-01
- NYSUT History Interview -- Tom Hobart; Chris Beecher (0207-06), 1992 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Part 3 -- 3/24/1992 --- #050-01
- NYSUT History Interviews: S. Feldman, W. Tice, G. Weinman, L. Swain (Box 3, Folder 18)
  #0207-12; #0207-13; #0207-14 & #0207-15
- NYSUT History Interview -- Jeannette DiLorenzo; Esther Aswad, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  4/27/1992 -- #0207-11 and #0207-21
- NYSUT Oral History Interviews 1990-2002 (Box 4)
- Charles Schumer's address to NYSUT at 1998 RA and 1999 RA (Box 5)
- Alan Lubin - Int. Dennis Gaffney, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  12/1/2004
- Alan Lubin, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  1/13/2005
- Alan Lubin Interview, 2004 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  12/7/2004
- Sylvia Matousale, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  3/27/2004
- Doug Matousek, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  3/24/2004
- Don McKellep, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  April 17, 2005
- Dan McKellep (tape 1), 2005 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  April 19, 2005
- Fred Nauman - tape 3, 2003 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  2003
- Fred Nauman 11/13 (a) (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Fred Nauman 11/13 (tape 2) (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Chuck Santelli, 2005 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  1/14/2005
- Chuck Santelli (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Dave Selden Interview #2 (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Shanker, Al UFT OH9 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  tape 1 -- user copy
- Shanker, Al UFT OH9 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  tape 2 -- user copy
- Shanker, Al UFT OH9 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  tape 3 -- user copy
- Shanker, Al UFT OH9 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  tape 4 -- user copy
- Shanker, Al UFT OH9 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  tape 5 -- user copy
- Eadie Shonkers -- May 19, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Eddie Shonker (May 19, 2009) (Box 25, Folder 1)
- Shonker/Hobart @ 1992 R.A. (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Disaffiliation Debate - 1976 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  Carrie Wynn (NEA) vs. Al Shonker (AFT)
- Herb Magidson -- 3/16/2005 (Box 28, Folder 1)
- James Wood (Box 29, Folder 1)
  Discussion of NYSUT History -- 1/3/2005
- Walter Tell (Box 30, Folder 1)
- Disaffiliation Tape - 1976 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  Laurie Wynn vs. Al Shonker
- Ken Deedy, May 12, 2004 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  (67)
- Ken Deedy / Tape 2 -- May 12, 2004 (Box 33, Folder 1)
- Vito Deleonardio (3/27/2004) (Box 34, Folder 1)
- Vito Deleonardise (Box 35, Folder 1)
- David Dorn -- 2005 (Box 36, Folder 1)
- Israel Kugler (Box 37, Folder 1)
- Israel Kugler 2 (Box 38, Folder 1)
- Camila Leiva / Samantha Johnson (Box 39, Folder 1)
- Camila Leiva --- Mexico! (Box 40, Folder 1)
- George Altomare 3 (Box 41, Folder 1)
- Antonia Cortese -- March 7, 2004 (Box 42, Folder 1)
- Tony Cortese 1 - Cont. (Box 43, Folder 1)
- A. Cortese - Ed. Reform -- 2/25/2005 (Box 44, Folder 1)
- Antonia Cortese -- 3/16/2005 (Box 45, Folder 1)
  Trips abroad
- Robert Allen interviewed by Denning Gaffney -- 9/24/2004 (Box 46, Folder 1)
- Robert Allen, 2004 (Box 47, Folder 1)
  Interviewed by D. Gaffney -- 9/24/2004 -- tape 2
- George Altomare -- Dec. 20, 2003 (Box 48, Folder 1)
- George Altomare 2 (Box 49, Folder 1)
- Tom Hobart Tape #1, 1990 (Box 50, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape of interview 12/10/1990; dub 1/3/2000
- Tom Hobart Tape #2, 1990 (Box 51, Folder 1)
- Tom Hobart Tape #3, 1990 (Box 52, Folder 1)
- Mark Corn (pt.2); Don Benker (pt.1), 2000 (Box 53, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape 4/6/2000
- Don Benker - Tape #2, 2000 (Box 54, Folder 1)
- Bob Allen; Antonia Cortese (tape 1), 1992 (Box 55, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape 1/4/2000 - Dub; 2/01/1992 - Interview
- Cortese (tape #2); James Wood, 2000 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape 2/01/1992; Dub - 1/4/2000
- Sylvia Matousek, 2000 (Box 57, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape 4/7/2000
- Vito DeLeonardis, 2000 (Box 58, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape 6/22/2000
- H. Magidson (tape #2), 2000 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape 1/5/2000
- Feldman; Tice; Weinman; Swain (tape #1), 1992 (Box 60, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape 4/1992
- Feldman; Tice; Weinman; Swain, 1992 (Box 61, Folder 1)
- Jeanette DiLorenzo; Esther Aswad, 1992 (Box 62, Folder 1)
  Cassette audio tape 4/27/1992
- Cole; Duesberg; Dunn, 1992 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  4/1992
- Doherty; Kafka (tape #1), 1992 (Box 64, Folder 1)
  2/1/1992; 1/4/2000 - Dub
- Manny Kafka (tape #2), 1992 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  2/1/1992; 1/4/2000-Dub
- Matousek; McCann - tape #1, 1992 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  2/18/1992; 1/4/2000 - Dub
- Bernard Ashe (tape #3), 2000 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  7/6/2000
- Bob Allen, Albany, 2000 (Box 68, Folder 1)
  June 15, 2000
- Tony Bifaro (tape #1), 2002 (Box 69, Folder 1)
  1/04/2002
- Bill Cea, 2000 (Box 70, Folder 1)
  4/7/2000
- Mike Corn (tape #1), 2000 (Box 71, Folder 1)
  4/6/2000
- Toni Cortese, Albany, 2000 (Box 72, Folder 1)
- Vito DeLeonardi, 2000 (Box 73, Folder 1)
  6/15/2000
- Dick Herrmann (tape #1), 2000 (Box 74, Folder 1)
- Lieberman; Magidson (tape #1), 1992 (Box 75, Folder 1)
  2/12/1992
- Dick Herrmann (tape 2), 2000 (Box 76, Folder 1)
- Tom Hobart (tape 1), 2002 (Box 77, Folder 1)
- Ely Kaplan, 2000 (Box 78, Folder 1)
  4/8/2000
- Fred Navman, 2000 (Box 79, Folder 1)
- Robert Paliwodzinski, Albany, NY, 2001 (Box 80, Folder 1)
  June 20, 2001
- Tom Pisa (tape 1); Albany, 2002 (Box 81, Folder 1)
  1/03/2002
- Paul Cole, 2000 (Box 82, Folder 1)
- Bernard Ashe (tape 1), Albany, 2000 (Box 83, Folder 1)
- Bernard Ashe (tape 2), Albany/NYC, 2000 (Box 84, Folder 1)
  6/15/2000; 7/6/2000
- Irwin Polishook (tape 1), 2002 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  1/17/2002
- Ed. Robisch (tape 1), NYC, 2002 (Box 86, Folder 1)
  1/5/2002
- Hobie Rhinehart, 2000 (Box 87, Folder 1)
- Gloria Weinman, 2000 (Box 88, Folder 1)
  4/16/2000